## NELSON KIPCHIRCHIR KIBINGE

Contact

Room OS1, OakField House

Information

Oakfield Grove// MRC IEU, University of Bristol

Tel: +447379009237

nelson.kibinge@bristol.ac.uk

Professional Summary A researcher, educator, and data scientist using data to understand problems in molecular biology, human health and education. I am a self-driven and motivated with extensive experience working with diverse teams and in lead roles involving the production of applied statistics and informatics data tools and code that have been utilized in clinical trials, epidemiological studies and academic purposes. As a PhD-trained computational biologist and statistician, I am involved in large-scale health research and also in teaching postgraduate courses at the university.

# CORE COMPETENCIES

- Biomarker discovery pipeline development
- Mendelian Randomization
- Clinical trial statistics
- Bayesian statistics
- Protein mass spectrometry
- protein microarrays
- Systems Biology
- Machine learning for biology
- Next generation sequencing (MiSeq and Oxford Nanopore)
- Compartmental Epidemiological Modeling
- Biostatistical programming: R and MATLAB
- Scripting languages: perl and python
- Unix shell scripting,
- Other applications: Machine learning tools such as support vector machines and decision tree modelling, LATEX, database, spreadsheet, and presentation software
- Capacity building
- Operating Systems: Unix/Linux, MacOSX.

## Professional Experience

#### Senior Research Associate

June 2019 to present

Genetic Epidemiology Lab, MRC IEU University of Bristol

# Senior Postdoctoral Scientist

Nov 2018 to present

Senior postdoctoral scientist leading the biostatistics and bionformatics department at the KEMRI-Wellcome Kilifi unit

KEMRI-Wellcome Trust Research Programe, Kenya

#### Visiting Research Fellow

Feb 2019 to Mar 2019

Project: Multi-center malaria antigen discovery project

University of Heidelberg Germany

# Visiting Research Fellow (Mathematical modeling) Feb 2017 to May 2017

 ${\bf Project:} \ \ \textit{Modeling the genetic diversification in RSV transmission}$ 

University of Warwick, United Kingdom

## Early Career Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Apr 2016 to Dec 2018

Project: Evaluating local respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) genetic diversity: a

 $statistical\ perspective$ 

Virus Epidemiology and Control Group,

KEMRI-Wellcome Trust Research Programe, Kenya

#### Research Assistant

Apr 2013 to March 2016

Project: Data mining methods for understanding gene expression in high throughput technologies

Computational systems biology laboratory, Nara Institute of Science and Technology Supervisor: Kanaya Shigehiko, Ph.D

#### Research Assistant

Jun 2007 to May 2008

Project: Biosafety; gene flow in wild oryzae sativa in Mwea region

School of Biological Sciences,

University of Nairobi

Supervisor: Samuel Kiboi, Ph.D

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### Part-time Lecturer

September 2017 to Present

MSc Course: Biostatistics and Research Methods

Courses taught: Biostatistics, databases and data visualization,

Research methods and experimental design

Department of Biochemistry, Pwani University, Kenya

## Teaching Assistant

Dec 2012 to Mar 2013

Bioinformatics II

Professor: Kensuke Nakamura

Department of Life Science and Informatics, Maebashi Institute of Technology, Japan

#### Teaching Assistant

Oct 2011 to Oct 2014

Systems Biology

Professor: Md Altaf-Ul-Amin

Graduate School of Information Science,

Nara Institute of Science and Technology, Japan

# OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE

# Medical Representative

Sep 2008 to Dec 2009

Pharmaken Limited Kenya

Nairobi office

#### EDUCATION

#### Nara Institute of Science and Technology (NAIST), Japan

Ph.D. Bioinformatics, March 2016

- Thesis title: Transcription regulation network analysis towards integrative big data biology
- Advisors: Shigehiko KANAYA, PhD and Naoaki ONO, PhD

M.Sc. Bioinformatics and biostatistics, March 2013

• Advisors: Shigehiko KANAYA, PhD and Kensuke NAKAMURA, PhD

#### University of Nairobi, Nairobi Kenya

B.Sc. Biology (First Class Honours), October 2008

• Advisor: Samuel Kiboi, Ph.D

## Funding and Awards

# Funding

- IDeAL postdoctoral funding Apr 2016 to Sep 2018 GBP: 175000
- TDModNet tropical disease modeling seed fund Jan 2017 to Jun 2017 GBP: 4600
- KEMRI Institutional Research Grant (IRG) June 2018 to Dec 2019 KES: 3967814

#### Awards

- Japanese Language studentship Osaka University Apr 2010 to Sep 2010
- Research Fellowship Oct 2010 to Mar 2011
- Masters Scholarship Apr 2011 to Mar 2013
- Doctoral Course Scholarship Apr 2013 to Mar 2016
- Gandhi Smarak Nidhi Trustee Fund Prize (Top undergraduate student SBS) May 2011

## Professional Membership

## Scientific Societies

May 2010 - Present

- Molecular Biology Society of Japan (MBSJ)
- International Society of Computational Biology (ISCB)
- African Society for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology (ASBCB)

#### Student Societies

July 2004 - Aug 2008

- Biology Association of Nairobi University Students(BANUS) July 2004 to July 2007
- Organising Secretary BANUS

Aug 2007 to July 2008

# REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- Kamuyu, G., Tuju, J., Kimathi, R., Mwai, K., Mburu, J., Kibinge, N., ... and Njunge, J. M. (2018). KILchip v1. 0: a novel Plasmodium falciparum merozoite protein microarray to facilitate malaria vaccine candidate prioritization. Frontiers in immunology, 9.
- Githinji, G., Agoti, C. N., Kibinge, N., Henson, S., Munywoki, P., Brand, S., ... and Worby, C. J. (2018). Assessing the utility of minority variant composition in elucidating RSV transmission pathways. bioRxiv, 411512.
- 3. Mohammed, K. S., **Kibinge, N.**, Prins, P., Agoti, C. N., Cotten, M., Nokes, D. J., and Githinji, G. (2018). Evaluating the performance of tools used to call minority variants from whole genome short-read data. *Wellcome Open Research*, 3.
- Njunge, J. M., Oyaro, I. N., Kibinge, N. K., Rono, M. K., Kariuki, S. M., Newton, C. R., and Gitau, E. N. (2017). Cerebrospinal fluid markers to distinguish bacterial meningitis from cerebral malaria in children. Wellcome Open Research, 2.
- Kibinge, N., Ono, N., Horie, M., Sato, T., Sugiura, T., Altaf-Ul-Amin, M. and Kanaya, S. (2016). Integrated pathway-based transcription regulation network mining and visualization based on gene expression profiles. *Journal of biomedical* informatics, 61, 194-202.
- 6. **Kibinge**, **N**., and Kiboi, S. (2016). Increasing the role of systems biology towards leveraging ecology research in Kenya. *CICSJ Bulletin Japan*, 34(2), 59.
- 7. Tanaka, N., Zakaria, N. A., **Kibinge, N.** K., Kanaya, S., Tamura, T., and Yoshida, M. (2014). Fall-risk classification of the timed up-and-go test with principal component analysis. *International journal of neurorehabilitation*, 1, e106-e106.

- 8. **Kibinge, N.**, Ikeda, S., Ono, N., Altaf-Ul-Amin, M., and Kanaya, S. (2014). Integration of Residue Attributes for Sequence Diversity Characterization of Terpenoid Enzymes. *BioMed Research International*, 2014.
- Ohtana, Y., Abdullah, A. A., Altaf-Ul-Amin, M., Huang, M., Ono, N., Sato, T.and Kibinge, N. K. (2014). Clustering of 3D Structure Similarity Based Network of Secondary Metabolites Reveals Their Relationships with Biological Activities. Molecular Informatics, 33(11-12), 790-801
- Afendi, F. M., Ono, N., Nakamura, Y., Nakamura, K., Darusman, L. K., Kibinge, N., and Kanaya, S. (2013). Data mining methods for omics and knowledge of crude medicinal plants toward big data biology. Computational and structural biotechnology journal, 4.
- 11. Ikeda, S., Abe, T., Nakamura, Y., Kibinge, N., Morita, A. H., Nakatani, A., ... and Kanaya, S. (2013). Systematization of the protein sequence diversity in enzymes related to secondary metabolic pathways in plants, in the context of big data biology inspired by the KNApSAcK Motorcycle database. Plant and Cell Physiology, pct041.

Manuscripts in Preparation/ Submitted

- 1. **Nelson Kibinge**, Charles Sande, Ken Mwai, George Githinji, Abdirahman Abdi, James Nokes and James Njunge, TransProt: An analysis pipeline for proteomic and transcriptomic data.
- 2. **Nelson Kibinge**, Samuel Brand, George Githinji, Charles Agoti, Lister Mirarwa, Everlyn Kamau, James Otieno and James Nokes, Sampling coverage and variant diversity capture in RSV surveillance *Manuscript in prep*.

CONFERENCE AND POSTER
PRESENTATIONS

- 1. **Nelson Kibinge**, Samuel Brand, George Githinji, Charles Agoti, James Otieno, Moses Kiti, Matthew Keeling and James Nokes (2017), Sampling considerations for optimizing genetic diversity capture in Respiratory Syncytial virus Surveilance *Epidemics 6 2017*, SItges, Spain, November 28-December 2, 2017
- Nelson Kibinge, Naoaki Ono, Masafumi Horie, Ming Huang, Tetsuo Sato, Tadao Sugiura, Md. Altaf-Ul-Amin, Saito Akira and Shigehiko Kanaya (2014), A systems mapping of transcription regulation in genes and modules of genes in lung cancer pathways, GIW-ISCB 2014, Odaiba, Tokyo, December 14-17, 2014.
- 3. Nelson Kibinge, Shun Ikeda, Naoaki Ono, Nakamura Kensuke, MD Altaf-Ul-Amin and Shigehiko Kanaya (2012). Utilizing metric properties of amino acids in distance matrix methods for protein sequence analysis BMB2012 The 35th annual meeting of the moleculars biology society of Japan Fukuoka, December, 11–14, 2012
- Nelson Kibinge, Shun Ikeda, Farit Afendi, Naoaki Ono, Nakamura Kensuke, MD Altaf-Ul-Amin and Shigehiko Kanaya (2012). Phylogenetic analyses suggest influence of parasitism on the genomes of malaria parasite. Genomics of Common Diseases 2012, Potomac MD, September 19-22, 2012
- Shun Ikeda, Manabu Ohi, Atsushi Nakatani, Nelson Kibinge, Naoaki Ono, Md. Altaf-UI-Amin, Shigehiko Kanaya (2012). Codon usage patterns of pathogenic bacteria. Genomics of Common Diseases 2012, Potomac MD, September 19-22, 2012

## Referees

Professor Philip Bejon

**Executive Director** 

Center for Geographic Medical Research

KEMRI-Wellcome Trust Kilifi P.O Box 230-80108 Kilifi

E-mail: pbejon@kemri-wellcome.org

Professor Suhaila Hashim

Head of Department

Department of Biochemistry

Center for Geographic Medical Research

Pwani University, Kenya P.O Box 195-80108 Kilifi Tel: +254707719757

E-mail: s.hashim@pu.ac.ke

## Dr. Samuel Kiboi

Senior Lecturer

School of Biological Sciences

University of Nairobi

P.O BOX 30197-00100

Nairobi

Tel: +254724580929

E-mail: samuel.kiboi@uonbi.ac.ke

# Professor Shigehiko Kanaya

Professor

Graduate School of Information Science Nara Institute of Science and Technology

8916-5 Takayama Ikoma

Nara 630-0101

 $Tel: \ +81\ 743\ 72\ 5952$ 

E-mail: skanaya@gtc.naist.jp